<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation of the Lords the Generall States, of the vnited Prouinces whereby the Spaniards and all their goods are declared to be lawfull prize: as also containing a strickt defence or restraint of sending any goods, wares, or merchandizes to the Spaniards or their adherents, enemies to the Netherlandes. Faithfully translated out of the Dutch coppy printed at S. Grauen Haghe by Aelbercht Heyndrickson, printer to the Generall States.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841231</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841231</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 557:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation of the Lords the Generall States, of the vnited Prouinces whereby the Spaniards and all their goods are declared to be lawfull prize: as also containing a strickt defence or restraint of sending any goods, wares, or merchandizes to the Spaniards or their adherents, enemies to the Netherlandes. Faithfully translated out of the Dutch coppy printed at S. Grauen Haghe by Aelbercht Heyndrickson, printer to the Generall States.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [E. Allde for] Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes-head Alley, neere .. Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; part of the imprint lacking on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> PROCLAMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE LORDS THE GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall States, of the
vnited Prouinces, whereby the Spaniards and all their goods are declared to be
lawfull prize: As alſo containing a ſtrickt defence or reſtraint of
ſending any goods, wares, or Merchandizes to the Spaniards or their
adherents, enemies to the Netherlandes.</p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of the Dutch coppy Printed at S.
Grauen Haghe by Aelbercht Heyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drickſon, Printer to the Generall States.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device bearing the initials "I.
W.".</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſolde at his
ſhop in Popes-head Alley, neere Exchange. <hi>1599.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5795:2"/>
            <head>A Proclamation, of the Lordes the <hi>generall States of the
vnited Prouinces,</hi> vvhereby the Spaniards and all their goods are declared
to be lawfull Prize. As alſo containing a ſtrict defence or reſtraint of
ſending any goods wares, or Merchandizes to the Spaniards or their
adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, enemies to the Netherlands.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall States of the vnited pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces. To all ſuch as
ſhall ſée or heare theſe preſents, make knowne: that whereas it
is euery day more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt apparant and manifeſt, that the
enterpriſes of the Spaniſh nation, with their conioyned adherents, hath not
béen only pretended to reduce theſe Netherlands by their deceitfull
practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the vttermoſt violence and force, vnder their wilfull and
ſuperbious dominion and tyrannicall gouernment, both ouer conſciences,
bodies, &amp; goods: But alſo that in the years paſt, they haue attempted,
with their vſual violent complots, to reduce the realmes of <hi>England</hi>
and <hi>Fraunce,</hi> vnder their power. Which they not being able (according
to their deſires to performe) now openly &amp; by maine force, aſſault
the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour countries of the Electors and Princes, and other Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall
places of the Empire, not refuſing to ouer-run the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and
Fortreſſes, with all manner of violence, batter them with péeces,
ranſomming them, and filling them with their ſouldiors, deſtroying the
flat land, rauiſhing and deflowring of women and maides, pilling, robbing,
murdering and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not fauouring the houſe or Caſtels of Princes,
Earles or Gentlemen, nor yet their perſons, as ſufficiently appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by
their barbarous dealings in the biſhoprick of <hi>Collen.</hi> the Dukedomes
of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Bergh,</hi> and the Biſhopricke of 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5795:2"/> 
               <hi>Munſter,</hi> and other bordering countries. The
miniſters of this ſpaniſh tyrannie boaſting, that according to their
own pleaſures they will proccede in their begunne actions, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in
theſe places, vntill ſuch time as they ſhall haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the whole
(beſides theſe Netherlandes) vnder their Spaniſh yoake, &amp; wholly
rooted out the exerciſe of the true Chriſtian religion. To which end they
haue publikely in diuers places of the Empire, altered the religion and
pollicie of the ſame, by force, threats, and other vndecent dealings.
Moreouer, vaunting to bee glad, that in the behalfe of the Princes Electors and
others, the armes be taken vp, for that they ſhall (as they ſay) the better
attaine the purpoſe. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that the new king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the
<hi>Infanta,</hi> and the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Counſell, as well in Spaine as in the
Low countries, deceitfully and forcibly, hinder and diſturbe al nauigations,
dealings, traffique, &amp; trade, ſo with inhabitants of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, as
with thoſe of other kingdomes, countries, and citties, in moſt barbarous
and tyrannicall ſort, miſvſing the perſons, attaching their ſhippes,
&amp; violating their graunted promiſes by water and land, all vnder the
pretence and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, becauſe that we haue hitherto ioyntly reſiſted
their falſe &amp; deceitfull dealings and haue not beene mooued to yeeld and
ſubuert the vnited Netherlands, and the good inhabitantes thereof, vnder
theſe barbarous tyrannie, and imperious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. And ſince that by gods
mightie power, the aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of her moſt excellent M. of England,
&amp; other kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; Common-weales, togither with our patience
and good endeuors, we haue for theſe many yeres withſtood theſe
ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall enterpriſes, (which they haue bent againſt al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome)
&amp; hope further, with Gods helpe and aſſiſtance (as aforeſaid) to
withſtand, &amp; there in are reſolued. Alſo to viſit the Spaniards in
the kingdoms &amp; lands by them occupied, not onely to hinder their
aforeſaid tyranous pretence, but alſo to recouer our loſſes &amp;
damages ſuſtained by them, aſwel with our ſhips of war, as by ſuch as
are allowed by our order, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping aſſuredly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his diuine Maieſtie wil
bleſſe our rightful &amp; <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5795:3"/> néedfull enterpriſes,
and once wholy frée and deliuer the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands from the aforeſaid
tyrannie of the Spaniards and their adherents. And alſo will mooue and incite
the neighbour Kings, Princes, Electors, Earles Barrons, and Common-wealthes,
that vppon good conſideration, they may take and vſe Armes, to aſſure
their perrillous eſtate, and to that ende, to driue out the Spaniards and
their complices, from the Emperours territories, and ſo out of the
Netherlands: as alſo wee finde to bee moſt expedient and neceſſary for
the accompliſhment of ſo Chriſtian lyke, rightfull, and néedfull
common cauſe, againſt the ſaid Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards and their conioyned adherents,
to be with all déepe inſight looked into, that there be not any
Shippes, goods or Marchandizes, ſent them by water, land, or otherwiſe, the
ſame beeing not onely permitted by the common people, but alſo the
emperiall rights and cuſtome of all Kings, Princes, and Common-weales, beeing
in warre or controuerſie, beſides that the ſame hath beene made knowne by
many firme orders and Proclaimations. As well by the aboue named the Queenes
Maieſtie of England, (with whome we are in ſure alliance) as alſo of
theſe countries. And we therefore intend not to permit that any perſon of
the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lands, vſing trafficke or fiſhing at ſea, or on the waters
within the land, ſhall ſuffer himſelfe to be deceiued, ſeduced, and
endamaged, by any deceitfull paſports, ſafegardes, or ſafe conducts of
the ſaid common enemie, as wee vnderſtand héeretofore (againſt our
good meanings) by ſome hath been done. So it is, that we vppon ripe and
profound deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by the aduiſe of the illuſtrious Prince and
Lord <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> borne Prince
of <hi>Orange,</hi> Counte of <hi>Naſſou,</hi> Marqueſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>de Vere, Fluſhing,
&amp;c.</hi> Gouernour and Captaine generall of <hi>Gelderland, Holland,
Zealand, Vtrecht, Oueryſel, &amp;c.</hi> as Admirall generall, haue declared,
and declare by theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, for good and lawfull prize, all perſons
and goods, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dominion of the Spaniſh king, in all places where they
ſhall or may be got, haue furthermore againe of new, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5795:3"/>
ſtricktly defended, forbidden, and reſpectiuely notified: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, forbid,
and notifie by theſe preſents, all and euerie one, of what condition,
realme, or land ſoeuer, none excepted, not to lade, ſhip, bring, or
tranſport by water or land, directly or indirectly, vnder what colour or
pretence ſoeuer, any ſhips, goods, wares, or merchandizes, for, or to any
hauen, cittie, or place of the enemie, in the kingdomes of <hi>Spaine,
Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall,</hi> or other places of <hi>Europe,</hi> vnder the dominion,
ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or commaund of the new king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Archduke
<hi>Albertus</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> or the Infanta of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
vppon paine of confiſcation of the ſame goods, wares, or merchandizes,
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſhippes, waggons, carts, and horſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or whereon
thy ſame ſhall bee laden, and all ſuch further puniſhment as hereafter
ſhall be declared.</p>
            <p>And to preuent all fraudes, ſubtile practiſes, and deceits,
which might in theſe vnited Netherlands be pretended by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, of what
countrie, condition, or quallitie ſo euer, againſt theſe our orders and
defences. Wee ordaine and command ſtricktly by theſe preſents, all
Conuoy-maiſters, Controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Searchers, and all other our Deputies in all
Hauens, Citties, and places of the ſame landes, vppon the oathe whereby they
are bound to their countrie vppon priuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their offices and arbitrall
correction: We authoriſe likewiſe all others, dwelling in the aforeſaide
vnited Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, or frequenting the ſame: dilligentlye to enquire, and to
take ſharpe regarde, if this our order bee by any one, of what countrie,
condition or qualitie ſoeuer, viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or broken.</p>
            <p>And if in the aforeſaid Hauens, Cities, or places, any goods be
laden, ſhipped, or carred, which being found, we will and ordaine them to be
ceazed &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> without common
courſe or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſhall bee
found to haue bene to laden togither with the ſhippes, waggons, Carts, and
horſes, to be confiſcated, the one third part to the vſe of the
accuſer, be he an officer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in ſeruice of the land or no,
and the other two third <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5795:4"/> parts, to the vſe of the common
cauſes, wherout the officer who ſhall follow the matter in law ſhall be
contented. Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning moreouer, that the proprietaries, or owners of the ſaid
goods, as alſo maiſters of the ſaid ſhips, waine men, or carmen, in
whoſe ſhips, or vpon whoſe waines or carts they ſhall be found to be
laden in the forbidden Hauens, Citties, and places, to be apprehended, and
ſtayed vntill ſuch time as they ſhall haue paide and accompliſhed al
ſuch further pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties and corrections, wherein according to the nature of
their treſpaſſe (by the arbitrements of the iudge) they ſhall be
condemned, which may not be leſſe (for ſo much as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the
Merchants) then a thouſand pounds. And for each of the Shippers or maiſters
of Ships, fiue hundreth pounds of fortie pence in the pound. And to the end
that the foreſaid orders may the better be followed, and all fraudes
puniſhed: We meane that within a yeare after the aforeſaide
treſpaſſe, all ſuch which ſhall bee found to haue violated or broken
the ſame, it ſhall and may be lawfull, by all officers of the ſaide
lands, and before competent Iudges, to arreſt and condemne them for the valew
of the ſaid goods and ſhippes, waggons, carts, and horſes, togither with
the aboue named penalties and corrections. The ſentence whereof by
prouiſion ſhall be executed, all appellations &amp; prouocations
notwithſtanding. And if any in the aforeſaid vnited Prouinces deſired to
ſhip or lade any goods, to tranſport the ſame to the neighbour countries
or friends: the ſame ſhall not bee permitted vnto him, vnleſſe he haue
leaue and licenſe thereto from vs, the ſaid Lord Admirall generall, or from
thoſe which therevnto by vs ſhall be appointed, and that by the ſhippes
which ſhall lade the ſame, ſufficient ſureties ſhall be ſet for the
valew of their ſhippes, that the ſaide laden goods ſhall not be carried
to any other place but to the hauens, citties, and places of our ſaid friends
and allies, and that within a certaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed reaſonable time named in
their paſports, according to the diſtance of the hauen, to yeeld
ſufficient certification and proofe thereof; or elſe their bond ſhall be
executed vppon the <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5795:4"/> ſureties, for the aforeſaid valew, to
the vſe of the common cauſes. And further, we charge all Admirals, Vice
Admirals Captaines, and Commiſſioners for ſea. All Chieftaines, Generals
of horſes, Captaines, and officers of men of war by land, to take ſharpe
regarde, that all ſuch of what lande or condition ſoeuer, as ſhall haue
any goods, wares, or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes in their ſhippes, vpon their waines,
Cartes, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or otherwiſe laden, being bound for the ſaide realmes,
countries and citties, held and occupied by the enemies, may be purſued,
ouertaken, and brought backe to the colleges of the Admiraltie, and other
iuſtices aforeſaide, to be puniſhed according to the tenor of theſe
preſents. And we being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to kéepe a good and ſure order
for the defence of the ſhips of trade and fiſhing, vſing at ſea,
againſt all forraine inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; robbings of the enemie, as alſo
againſt the exorbitant ranſomes which the common enemies vſe in the
pilling and ranſoming of the ſame. We haue therefore forbidden and
interdicted, forbid and interdicte by theſe preſents, all inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of
the vnited lands, aſwel Merchants Ships, Pilots, as other, vſing trafficke
or fiſhing, at Sea or on the Riuers within the land, or tranſporting any
goods beyond the ſeas, to take or procure any paſports or ſafegards of
the enemies, in no maner of ſort, vpon confiſcation of the ſhips and
goods of ſuch as ſhall be found to haue taken any, with further ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrall
correction. Ordaining that the giuers of the ſaid paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, ſafegardes,
or ſafe conductes of the common enemie, ſhall bee for example of other,
puniſhed by loſſe of life, and confiſcation of theyr goods, as ayders
of the enemy. And if in caſe any of the ſhips or Pilots be by the enemie
taken, and ouer and aboue the order by vs therto eſtabliſhed, be
ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed and endamaged, we will and ordaine that the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable
ranſomes and damages ſhall be recouered vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on the Officers, Iuſtices, and ſubiects of the vilages of
<hi>Bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant, Flaunders,</hi> and
others, remaining vnder the enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, beſides what they ſhall pay to the comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> or for ranſome, charging and authorizing the deputed
counſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5795:5"/> of the
States of the reſpectiue Prouinces, whoſe ſubiects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe our
orders ſhall be by the common enemie by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant and vnreaſonable
ranſomes or otherwaies endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged, to take notice thereof, and to recouer
and remburſt them as before, by ſuch proceedings and meanes of executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
as in like matter is commonly vſed. And to the ende no man pretend ignorance
hereof, we ſignifie and commaund our beloued, the States, Lieutenants, and
appointed Counſailors of the States, and deputed States of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue
Prouinces of <hi>Gelderland, Holland, Zealand, Verecht, Vrieſland,
Oueryſſel, Grooning,</hi> and <hi>Omlanden,</hi> and all other Iuſtices,
and Officers vnto whom it dooth belong: to cauſe this our will and ordinance
to be euery where publiſhed and proclaimed, in the places where the publique
Proclimations are vſually proclaimed, we charge likewiſe the Chauncelor,
Preſidents, and prouinciall Counſailours, Aduocates, Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals, and
generall Atturneys: and all other Officers, Iudges and Iuſtices of the
aforeſaide Countries, together with all Chéefetaines, Coronels,
Admirals, Vice-admirals, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of Horſes, Captaines, Officers and
Commaunders, to follow and enſue theſe our ordinances, and to cauſe them
to be followed and enſued, procéeding and cauſing to be
procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt the tranſgreſſors thereof, without grace,
fauour, diſſimulation or delaye, as we haue found the ſame for the Lands
welfare to bee moſt néedfull. Giuen in <hi>S. Grauen Haghe,</hi> the
ſecond of Aprill. 1599.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. van oldenbarnevelt v. By the
order of the aforeſaid Lordes the Generall States.</signed> 
               <signed>C. Aerſſen,</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5795:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
